all right
[Music]
the vegan diet as a neglected cause of
psychosis
a tragic story of a 47 year old woman
with a five-year history of psychosis
treated with antipsychotics years of
hallucinations
finally her mother revealed that the
patient was following a strict vegan
diet for seven years and was not
supplementing with vitamin B12
they started giving her B12 supplements
and eventually her psychiatric symptoms
went away but she spent five years of
her life in a psychotic Haze because she
wasn't getting a regular reliable source
of vitamin B12
B12 supplements or sufficient intake of
B12 fortified Foods is mandatory for
vegans and effective but only if you do
it like in the largest study vegans in
history the event is to study the
prevalence of low vitamin B12 status was
the same between vegans vegetarians and
meat eaters why presumably because they
were eating fortified foods and
supplements the researchers concluded
the encouragement of vitamin B12
supplementation cannot be overemphasized
vitamins B12 and D are the only two
vitamins not made by plants B12 is made
by microbes and vitamin D is made by
animals such as ourselves when we walk
outside it's the sunshine vitamin some
other nutrients are only found
concentrated in certain plants though
and you can become deficient if you
don't eat them for example this case of
a 10 year old girl with night blindness
she couldn't see well at night vitamin A
deficiency was the Doctor's first stop
but the kid was vegetarian and so
getting whopping doses of beta-carotene
and all the vegetables she ate which
your body turns into Vitamin A almost as
an afterthought as they were leaving the
office the doctor just asked the mother
I assume she's getting plenty of
vegetables right but no she does not
like vegetables and only eats like I
don't know Ritz crackers or something so
with something like vitamin A it's easy
getting enough eating greens or any of
the orange fruits and vegetables like
mangoes sweet potatoes carrots or
cantaloupe but you actually have to eat
fruits and vegetables a vegan living off
a diet of fast food is at a greater risk
for vitamin A deficiency than a meat
eater living on fast food because at
least the cow ate some greens and passed
it along
iodine is a similar situation cow's milk
is a primary source of dietary iodine in
the United States not because cows
somehow synthesize iodine or any other
element iodine and milk comes from the
leaching of iodine containing
disinfectants used to clean contaminated
Udders and milking equipment into the
milk or from supplements fed to cattle
regardless those not drinking milk or
eating seaweed which is an even better
Source may be an increased risk for
iodine deficiency
I've studied vegans in the UK suggest as
many as 90 aren't getting enough in
their diet though this is likely an
overestimate since their food frequency
questionnaire didn't include seaweed or
iodized salt two of the ways some may be
getting it are there reports of it
actually causing problems yes indeed
veganism as a cause of iodine deficient
hypothyroidism 23 month old boy
breastfed until 16 months of age then
weaned on a strictly plant-based diet
without iodized salt mom was fine
presumably because of the iodine and
their prenatal vitamins as she continued
to take which spilled over into her
breast milk the American thyroid
Association is very clear about
recommending that pregnant and
breastfeeding women take a prenatal with
150 micrograms of iodine a day
most kids in the U.S transition from
breast milk to cow's milk but those who
don't need to get their iodine from
somewhere thankfully after an iodine
containing multivitamin his deficiency
cleared that's one way taking
supplements like the cows do but sea
vegetables are the healthiest source of
iodine a half teaspoon of mild seaweeds
like army or Dulce should get all the
iodine you need for the day you can just
have a Shaker of dose flakes at the
kitchen table or two Nori sheets of
seaweed that's my favorite method
because you can just eat them like a
snack in fact probably the healthiest
snacks since you're snacking on dark
green leafy vegetables
there was also a recent report of severe
iron deficiency anemia attributed to a
plant-based diet in Menorah which means
excess blood loss during menstruation a
21 year old woman presented with reduced
Vision in one of her eyes because a vein
clotted off which can happen when you
get really anemic thankfully her vision
resolved after taking iron supplements
now according to the American dietetic
Association the incidence of iron
deficiency anemia among vegetarians is
no worse than that of non-vegetarians so
it may have just been her excess monthly
blood loss but a more recent review
questioned the official position that
iron deficiency anemia appears no more
prevalence among vegetarian women than
among non-vegetarian women the updated
review claimed to find four studies
where this wasn't the case where
vegetarians had a significantly higher
rates yet here's the four studies and as
always I'll put links to them in the
sources cited section beneath this video
on nutritionfacts.org so you can read
them yourself like I do for every study
I cite in my videos and not a single one
backed up that statement
but just because vegetarians don't have
worse anemia rates than non-vegetarians
that's not saying much since after one
in 20 menstruating women suffer from
iron deficiency anemia across the board
having lower iron stores is actually
advantageous as I've done videos about
yet another reason to consume more
plants and Less meat but if your blood
count is dropping if your hemoglobin is
getting too low then you can enhance
iron absorption by eating vitamin C rich
foods with your meals so fresh fruit
bell peppers broccoli Etc and since
especially tea but also coffee can
inhibit iron absorption you shouldn't
drink them with meals
foreign